Xiao Han

CONTACT Information Department of Computer Science

Utah State University Email: hanxiao2099@gmail.com

Phone: (541) 908-8790

4205 Old Main Hill Github: hanxiao0607 Logan, UT 84322 Page: personal site

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research interests lie in the field of data mining, machine learning, and artificial intelligence, with a particular focus on anomaly detection, fairness-aware machine learning, root cause analysis, and reinforcement learning.

EDUCATION

Utah State University, Logan, UT Aug 2020 - Present

Ph.D. candidate in Computer Science

Advisor: Dr. Shuhan Yuan

George Washington University, Washington, DC Aug 2018 - May 2020

M.S. in Data Analytics

Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR Sep 2014 - Dec 2017

M. Eng. in Computer Science

Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong, China Sep 2008 - May 2012

B. Eng. in Computer Science and Technology

Honors and Awards Presidential Doctoral Research Fellowship, Utah State University, 2020 - 2024

Graduate Student Travel Award, Utah State University, 2023

Student Travel Award, IEEE BigData, 2021

Student Travel Award, CIKM, 2021

Continued Success Scholarship, Oregon State University, 2015

Publications and Preprints

Publications

- Xiao Han, Lu Zhang, Yongkai Wu, and Shuhan Yuan. Achieving Counterfactual Fairness for Anomaly Detection. In Pacific-Asia Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining. (PAKDD). 2023.
- Xiao Han, Depeng Xu, Shuhan Yuan, and Xintao Wu. Few-shot Anomaly Detection and Classification Through Reinforced Data Selection. In 2022 IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM). 2022.
- 3. Xiao Han, He Cheng, Depeng Xu, and Shuhan Yuan. InterpretableSAD: Interpretable Anomaly Detection in Sequential Log Data. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data). 2021.
- 4. Xiao Han and Shuhan Yuan. Unsupervised cross-system log anomaly detection via domain adaptation. In Proceedings of the 30th ACM International Conference on Information & Knowledge Management. (CIKM). 2021.

Preprints

1. Xiao Han, Lu Zhang, Yongkai Wu, and Shuhan Yuan. On Interpretable Anomaly Detection Using Causal Algorithmic Recourse. arXiv preprint. 2022.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning and AI Intern, Nokia Bell Labs

Murray Hill, NJ

Jun 2023 - Present

- Conducted a patent application as part of the research team.
- Developed research on anomaly detection for log data, leveraging reinforcement learning techniques specifically designed for large language models.

• Implemented a robust framework using PyTorch to effectively address the challenges associated with anomaly detection.

Research Assistant, Utah State University

Logan, UT

 $\rm May~2022$ - $\rm May~2023$

Aug 2020 - Aug 2021

- Developed an framework (InterpretableSAD) to detect anomalies in sequential log data. Applied data augmentation and interpretable machine learning techniques to enhance performance.
- Implemented a transfer-learning framework (LogTAD) using adversarial domain adaptation for detecting anomalies across multiple systems. Utilized transfer learning principles to improve detection accuracy.
- Created a framework (FADS) for few-shot anomaly detection and classification. Incorporated semi-supervised and reinforcement learning techniques to enhance performance with limited labeled samples.
- Designed a framework (CFAD) to ensure counterfactual fairness in anomaly detection. Maintained consistent detection outcomes while considering causation-based fairness.
- Built a framework (ADCAR) for root cause analysis in anomaly detection. Identified abnormal features and provided actionable recommendations using causal inference techniques.
- Produced an interpretable anomaly detection framework focusing on explanations and recommended recourse actions in time series anomaly detection.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, Department of Computer Science

Utah State University, Logan, UT

Aug 2021 - May 2022

- CS 5665 Introduction to Data Science
- CS 6665 Data Mining

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: C++, Java, Python, Haskell, SQL

Database Systems: MySQL, MongoDB, ArangoDB, SQLite Developer Tools: Linux, Unix, Git, Jetbrains, AWS, Databricks Certification: Certified Information Systems Auditor (CISA)

Synergistic Activities

Conference Reviewer

• IEEE International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN) 2023

Journal Reviewer

- ACM Transactions on Modeling and Performance Evaluation of Computing Systems
- Elsevier Computers & Security Reviewer
- Frontiers in Big Data
- IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security
- IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems
- IEEE/CAA Journal of Automatica Sinica
- International Journal of Data Science and Analytics